ILGWU. Miscellany, 5780/200
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Miscellany
1904-1986
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
5780/200
5.67 cubic feet
5.7 linear feet
Publications, minutes, records.
This collection contains assorted periodicals, including issues of Justice, Giustizia, and Die Gleichheit.
7128067
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
July 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, July 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains assorted periodicals, including issues of Justice, Giustizia, and Die Gleichheit.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU records
5780/061. ILGWU. Miscellany
General
"Permanent deposit"
Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Women's clothing industry -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Industrial relations -- New York (State); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
7128067
- Bound book of meeting minutes, 1904-1911 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Wrapped in tissue paper. Mostly handwritten. Very brittle
- Jerusalem The Saga of the Holy City, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Limited edition copy
- Givstizia, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Justice in Italian. Bound issues (Jan. 1930-Mar. 1931) Very brittle
- Scrap book – The I.L.G.'er, Upper South Dept. and Baltimore Joint Board, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  May 1956-May 1959. 8 copies
- Giustizia (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Justice in Italian. Bound issues. Very brittle
- ILGWU News-History, 1900-1950, ILGWU Golden Jubilee Convention, Atlantic City – Booklet – 3 copies (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Advertisement from – Fashion of the Times – magazine (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Amerika, no. 65 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- The Dead Sea Scrolls of the Hebrew University, edited by E.L. Sukenik, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Die Gleichheit, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Justice in Yiddish. Bound issues. Very brittle
- The Gleichheit, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- The Gleichheit, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- The Gleichheit, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- The Gleichheit, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- S/ant on Western Massachusetts District, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  vol.1,no.1-2 (1958); vol.2,no.1- 2 (1958); vol.3,no.3-9 (1958)
- The Springfield Massachusetts Sunday Republican, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  May 28, 1961. Brittle
- Arbitration of grievances, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Acceptability as a Factor in Arbitration under an Existing Agreement by William E. Simkin, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- The Arbitration Journal, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Sept. 1986
- The Gleichheit, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- The Gleichheit, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- The Gleichheit, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- The Gleichheit, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- The Gleichheit, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Justice, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Bound issues. Very brittle. 2 copies
- Justice, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Bound issues. Very brittle
- Justice, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Justice, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Justice, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Folder of correspondence and reports from Green Dolmatch Inc. Advertising (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Folder with miscellaneous correspondence about advertising (Box 5, Folder 2)
- The News, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Thurs., Jan. 31,1980. Partial issue
- Turkey-The Tasty Impostor. by Craig Claiborne with Pierre Franey (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Laminated (appears to be a published recipe)
- Decatur Weekly News, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Thurs., Feb. 28, 1935 issue (photocopy copy, original too brittle to keep)
- Justice - bound issues from 1971 brittle (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Bound issues. Brittle
- Justice – bound issues from 1969 brittle (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Justice – bound issues from 1970 brittle (Box 5, Folder 8)
- The New Post, 1910-1911 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Very brittle
- The New Post, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Scrapbook of news clippings, 1941-1946 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook of news clippings, 1950-1957 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  miscellaneous other years are included 'loose' inside the front cover, all clippings are Very brittle
- Scrapbook of news clippings, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  Inside the front cover is a handwritten note "This scrap book was fixed by Ruby Taylor. Her daughter Ada Gordon gave it to Anne Donaley who is giving it to the Illinois Ladies Garment Workers Union, July 16, 1984" Very brittle (place in mylar to try to keep it together)
- Scrapbook news clippings and other items., 1978-1980 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  Some items are brittle
- Miscellaneous papers taken out of 5780 O (oversize) – Statements, correspondence, etc. (Box 9, Folder 1)